<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-25T14:05:50+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mathurin Massias’ webpage</title><subtitle>Mathurin Massias</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Advice for CNRS and INRIA recruitment</title><link href="/cnrs_inria_advice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Advice for CNRS and INRIA recruitment" /><published>2024-07-25T09:41:41+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-25T09:41:41+00:00</updated><id>/cnrs_inria_advice</id><content type="html" xml:base="/cnrs_inria_advice/"><![CDATA[<p>INRIA and CNRS “chargé de recherche” positions offer unique conditions of freedom to do first-grade research: lifelong contract, no teaching involved. The application process is  challenging, but it’s definitely worth it! The goal of this guide is to make the application process as easy as possible.</p>

<p>It only reflects my particular opinion and limited experience of going through it, and helping people with it for the last 3 years.
Feedback is most welcome!</p>

<p>INRIA has issued a very useful guide: <a href="https://www.inria.fr/sites/default/files/2021-01/CE_guide-applicant-CRCN.pdf">Advice for Applicants for a Young Graduate Scientist Position at Inria</a>.</p>

<p>TLDR:</p>
<ul>
  <li>the application requires lots of work and communication with the teams you apply to: start in october</li>
  <li>show 5 to 10 years ambition in your research project, depart from your PhD works</li>
  <li>do not be too technical, neither in the research project, nor in the audition</li>
  <li>keep in mind that most members of the jury are not expert in your research area</li>
  <li>ask for a lot of feedback on every part of your application (project discussion and proofreading, audition rehearsals)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="most-important-advice-talk-to-many-people">Most important advice: talk to many people</h3>
<p>Those selection processes are very peculiar and very different from what you’ve been used to in your PhD and postdoc. <strong>You need to talk to as many people as possible!</strong> There are three categories of person to contact:</p>
<ul>
  <li>senior researchers having been involved in the process for several years. Talking to past members of the jury is priceless: they will tell you what the jury is looking for in candidates! Current members of the jury will rightfully decline speaking with you, as this is not ethical. Do not put them in an uncomfortable position by contacting them.</li>
  <li>heads and members of the various teams you apply to. They should give you feedback on your application file, and organize rehearsals with you. If they don’t, it’s not a very good sign.</li>
  <li>successful past candidates. They will tell you what worked and what didn’t for them. The yearly results are public and for example available on <a href="https://www.coudert.name/concours_cnrs_2024.html">FX Coudert’s website</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Gather as much advice as possible, even if they end up disagreeing: you’ll make your own choices when the time comes.</p>

<p>Do not be afraid of contacting people, even if you don’t know them. Most people are happy to help. Worst can happen is people don’t answer your email. If they don’t, send at least two follow-up emails, waiting around 2 weeks between each. This is typical practice and will not be interpreted as pushy if you are polite in your mail (and concise! go to the point to save people’s time).</p>

<p>Have your PhD and postdoc advisors help you too.</p>

<h3 id="global-timeline-start-in-october">Global timeline: start in October!</h3>
<p>The CNRS deadline is usually around the beginning of January (in 2024 it was more end of January, we’ll see if it’s a permanent change), the Inria one is end of January/February. <strong>You must contact the potential hosting teams around October</strong> of the previous year, not after. The teams will ask you to come do a presentation to evaluate your compatibility and discuss a common project, and they will give feedback on your research project.
All this takes time, so do not wait for December to do it. A team may be interested by your profile, but already have candidates.</p>

<p><strong>Laying out a full research project for 5/10 years requires several months of intensive work</strong>, so you should start writing around October too.</p>

<h3 id="cnrsinria-differences">CNRS/INRIA differences</h3>
<p>Disclaimer: I know INRIA better.</p>

<p>In CNRS the recruitment is national, and you <em>suggest</em> 2 or 3 teams for your integration (if you get accepted, CNRS decides where to send you, which may or may not be one of those teams).
You mention the teams, each in a paragraph, at the end of your research project, and spend 30 seconds per team at the end of your oral presentation, to explain why they’d be a good match.
You should still work on your integration and know what the people in the team are doing, and how you’d like to work with them, but the philosophy is, very roughly, that you should be able to lead your research in any lab, and that the surrounding people do not matter this much (my 2 cents from gathered feedbacks). This may differ between section 7 (computer science) and 41 (maths).</p>

<p>INRIA is very different: you have one application file per Inria center (there are 9 in France). Inside a center, you apply for a team (you have the possibility to not specify one, but it makes a bad impression: it means that there is no team for which you are a perfect fit).
Your application file is thus very different from CNRS: the targeted team must appear frequently in it. In your whole research project, you must show what you will bring them, what they can help you with, why you are similar but complementary, who you’ll interact with, etc.</p>

<p>Finally, for INRIA, since you apply in a team, its support is essential. Even more that for CNRS, you should contact the hosting team early.</p>

<h3 id="document-1-summary-of-past-research">Document 1: Summary of past research</h3>
<p>Show that there is coherence in your past works, that you took initiatives, that all your works interact nicely in a grand scheme that defines your identity and uniqueness as a researcher. it should not be perceived as a sequence of unrelated works that were proposed by your PhD advisors.
<strong>Do not be too technical</strong>, summarize in layman’s term. Show that you understood what were the big challenges of your field, and how you contributed to solving them.</p>

<h3 id="document-2-the-research-project">Document 2: The research project</h3>
<p>Writing the research project is the hardest (but also very interesting) part of the application. <strong>Ask at least 3 successful candidates from past years their research project, to see what worked</strong>.</p>

<h4 id="the-right-balance-ambitious-but-realistic">The right balance: ambitious but realistic</h4>
<p>Writing the research project is a very different exercise from what we’re used to in PhD/postdoc research statement.
Understand that CNRS and INRIA chargé de recherche are lifelong positions. In your project, you must show that you have research ideas for your whole life, and not just for the next 3 years. The difficulty is that your project should:</p>
<ul>
  <li>be ambitious: show that you have a direction for roughly the next 10 years</li>
  <li>be realistic: show why you have the tools to solve the problems you’ll consider</li>
</ul>

<p>Ideally, you give big directions in which you want to go, and descriptions of concrete ways with which you would start. People usually divide their project into 3 liked axis; each axis should start with something simple (one research idea that you could start working on as soon as you get the position), and then aim for something more distant, that has the right to be less precise.
The jury knows that research is hard to predict (you won’t probably do everything in your project), but they want to see that you have a plan.</p>

<p><strong>You should avoid at all cost giving the impression that you’ll continue working exactly on what you did during your PhD</strong>. This would make the jury fear that once this line of work dries up, you’ll be left without ideas. You should show thematic mobility, while remaining coherent with your past research…</p>

<h4 id="composition-of-the-jury-speak-to-everybody">Composition of the jury: speak to everybody</h4>
<p>Your application will be read in details by 1 or 2 expert reviewers, that know your field very well. But, beware that the rest of the jury will be much less familiar with your line of work, and most probably only skim through the introduction. Having a look at the composition of the jury (it is public, for example <a href="https://section7.cnrs.fr/#composition">here for Section 7 of CNRS</a>) is a good idea to realize the diversity of your audience - and to guess who your reviewer will be. They are usually the one that ask the first questions during the audition, so knowing their interests helps you prepare.</p>

<p>In short: <strong>be precise, for the specialists, but be understandable, for the rest of the jury</strong>. We tend to focus on the first part and ignore the second.</p>

<p>To speak to everybody: why is your problem important? which locks do you unlock? how is this different from what everybody does in the field? what are the current barriers in the field and why are you, with your experience, drive and ideas, the perfect person to lift them?
You need to display maturity, global vision of your field: basically that you’re ready to be an independent, permanent researcher, no longer someone following a mentor.
Show that what you’re working on has impact, that it’s not a small niche that you plan to exploit all your life: your work should unlock new research venues, be important to others too. Show that these questions are interesting for others, beyond you (using citations for example).</p>

<p>People not so familiar with your field should understand why you’re unique.
As a personal example: all optimizers (me included) tend to mention that they want to develop faster algorithms, with better guarantees, and less data-hungry. But do some people look for slow algorithms that don’t work and need more data? This does not characterize you at all. Be more precise.</p>

<p>In your project: why are you legitimate for this? What have you accomplished that proves you’ll be able to do all this? Which tools do you master that others don’t?</p>

<p>Give illustrations, give orders of magnitude, do periodic recaps in your talk.  <strong>Never underestimate how quickly someone, even expert, can lose track of what you say</strong>. It is not the time to be subtle: write stuff in bold for members of the jury that will cross-read your research project while you’re talking.</p>

<p>Do not write too much maths, it’s very hard to parse in a short presentation. Show that you are able to popularize your research, to speak to many. <strong>Technicality is the enemy here, you’re not writing a research article, not even an abstract</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="the-oral">The oral</h3>
<h4 id="timing">Timing</h4>
<p>Presentations are short (15 min for CNRS section 7, 20 min for Inria). There is no room for approximation or hesitation, your presentation must be meticulously prepared.</p>

<p>The usual plan is:</p>
<ul>
  <li>1 slide of career summary (place and topics for PhD and Postdocs)</li>
  <li>introduction to research field through selected past works (preferably 2)</li>
  <li>research project</li>
  <li>for CNRS, 1 slide integration details (1 min)</li>
  <li>finish with 1 slide of recap that you leave displayed after the presentation, summarizing who you are</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>The research project is the critical part of the presentation and should take around two-thirds of the presentation.</strong>
On the contrary, presentation of your career and past works basically only serves to justify why you are the ideal person to carry on this research project.
Be quick on these parts, don’t brag too much. <strong>See it as a stepping stone for the real deal: your project</strong>.</p>

<h4 id="practical-organization-of-the-audition-and-its-consequences-for-you">Practical organization of the audition and its consequences for you</h4>

<p>For CNRS: the jury gathers for 1 week, hears roughly 35 candidates (7/8 per day). Then the weekend passes, and they meet for 3 days to rank them. That is a lot, and draining.
When they meet on day 6, one week has passed since they heard the first candidates. They do take notes, but <strong>your goal is to help them remember you</strong>.</p>

<p>They should think: “ah yes, X is the girl who wanted to do this, with those tools, and had done Z in the past”. To achieve this, <strong>it should be very clear for you who you are as a researcher</strong> (which problems you like to work on, what is your methodology to solve them, do you like theory, or practice, or both? Do you want applications?). Then, your goal is to communicate that to the jury.</p>

<p>You need to tell a story, that should be reflected in your research project’s name.
This is a step back on your research that is probably new, but mandatory.</p>

<h4 id="adapted-content">Adapted content</h4>
<p>The composition of the jury is very important. Out of roughly 15 persons, maybe 2 or 3 only work in your domain.
Even more than in the research project (that, I think, many members of the jury do not read), it is very important that you <strong>speak to everybody</strong>, at least in the introduction and in your first 2-3 slides.
You should aim at getting questions from more than 5 persons in the audience, not just the 2-3 experts.</p>

<p>In order not to lose the other members of the jury:</p>
<ul>
  <li>your introduction slides should speak to them in general terms</li>
  <li>having applied examples and drawings helps</li>
  <li>periodically (especially, when moving from past research to project), remind the audience what you’ve said, and where you’re going, in layman’s term</li>
</ul>

<p>Various stuff:</p>
<ul>
  <li>avoid being too technical (heavy notation, figures that are hard to parse). It’s already very hard to convey information in 15 minutes, be simple.</li>
  <li><strong>avoid long sentences and heavy slides</strong></li>
  <li>it’s advised to have 1 slide per minute. If you have more, you probably have too much content.</li>
  <li>using clear color codes help (e.g. using the same color for a variable in an equation and the corresponding words in the associated sentence); you can also use repeatedly the same color code (green/orange) for short term/long term goals, etc</li>
  <li><strong>pretty slides matter</strong>. It is not uncommon to spend 2 full weeks on them. Dry slides are to avoid at all costs, they lose the jury’s attention. Use colors, illustrations, boxes around important content.</li>
  <li>have backup technical slides if you want</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="rhythm">Rhythm</h4>

<p>You should know your presentation by heart, especially because you’re likely to be stressed in the beginning.
Then hopefully after a few seconds you get into the presentation; knowing the intro by heart helps getting through this hard phase.
Be prepared to speak exactly for the amount of time you’re allowed; if it’s too short you missed an opportunity to convey messages, if it’s too long you may get interrupted and appear unprepared.</p>

<p>Do not try to force as much content as possible; on the contrary, taking breaks to summarize what you just said (e.g. after your past works, and before diving into your project) allows jury members outside of your area of expertise to catch up. Remember, you can lose them more easily than you think.</p>

<h4 id="questions">Questions</h4>
<p>The questions session lasts between 15 min (CNRS) and 20 (INRIA). Answer precisely and concisely. It’s very frustrating for the jury to not be able to ask all their questions for lack of time, because the candidate took too much time to answer some questions.
It’s OK to say that you don’t know, don’t lie.</p>

<p>Some frequent questions:</p>
<ul>
  <li>“if you got funding for a PhD student when you arrive, what would they work on?”. Show that you have thought about it, and that you have a plan (in particular, you don’t have HDR, so you’ll need to take cosupervise the student: with which team member?).</li>
  <li>“what is THE big problem that you’d want to solve in the next 10 years” this is clearly related to the big question “who are you as a researcher?” whose answer must be crystal clear for you</li>
  <li>“what is the work that you’re the most proud of”: show that you are able to evaluate your own work, to take a step back on it. It also defines who you are: you like this work because of its practical impact, because it solved a theoretical question, etc.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="learn-the-many-implicit-rules">Learn the many implicit rules</h3>
<p>This is a major reason why you should discuss with people: there are many little unwritten things to know. For example, the year I applied to CNRS, in addition to section 7, I applied for section 41, but in the “mathematics” track. Little did I know that, as an optimizer, I belonged to the “mathematics and applications” track (I did not get auditioned in section 41 :).</p>

<p>For some projects, it’s important to show that you handle applications; for some it’s not, etc. You can only learn of all this by talking to experienced people.</p>

<p>For CNRS, know the different culture and expectations between Sections 6, 7 and 41.</p>

<p>For INRIA, know that the jury likes to see that your project has an applicative part, and a methodological part.</p>

<p>Show that you have been proactive in your preparation: instead of saying “this is something I plan on discussing with member of X of the team”, do it before the audition. If, when you arrive in the team, you plan to go to somebody to obtain data, contact them before the oral. This way you can show the jury that you’ve already done stuff.</p>

<!-- epart from what you did previously. it gave you tools and techniques to address a bigger problem, but avoid at all cost giving the impression that you find a nice little niche domain to work on, that you'll continue exploiting for a few years and then run out of ideas.
 -->]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[INRIA and CNRS “chargé de recherche” positions offer unique conditions of freedom to do first-grade research: lifelong contract, no teaching involved. The application process is challenging, but it’s definitely worth it! The goal of this guide is to make the application process as easy as possible.]]></summary></entry></feed>